<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>other build systems</title>
    <author email="email@invalid">Yiannis Paschalidis</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <!--  Section uses an H2, so use H3 and below for sub-sections. -->
    <section name="Getting started - Command-line">

<p>This guide shows how to get a simple "Hello World" bLight application
up and running using command-line tools. For simplicity, this example is a 
command-line application which runs and template and then exits. It is
not an example of good practice, as it omits nicities such as error handling,
logging and unit testing. The complete source code and configuration discussed 
here can be downloaded together in a single 
<a href="../blight-example-cmdline-helloworld-src.zip">zip file</a>.</p>

<p>bLight includes a command-line interface to the template compiler to allow
integration with other build systems. An example built using the command-line
is shown below.</p>

<p>Templates should be placed together with your other Java code under
<code>src/main/java</code>. It is recommended that templates are placed in 
their own package. In the example, the application consists of the 
main <code>MyApp</code> application class, and a single template
named <code>MyTemplate</code>. The <code>lib</code> directory will eventually
contain the libraries required to build and run the application.</p>
 
<source>
/
|-- lib/
`-- src/
    `-- main/java/example/mycompany/myapp/
        |-- MyApp.java
        `-- templates/
            `-- MyTemplate.java
</source>

<h3>Java code</h3>

<p>The bLight Java API is quite small. There are only two classes which you need to be familiar
with - <code>AbstractTemplate</code> which is the default parent class for all templates, and  
the <code>TemplateManager</code> which executes templates.</p>

<h4>MyApp.java</h4>

<p>The application code creates a template, sets the output to System.out and executes the template.
<em>Note</em>: While it is possible to execute templates directly, it is recommended to always use
the TemplateManager. This allows for dynamic template compilation (see below) during development 
without requiring an application restart each time a template is changed.</p>

<source>
package example.mycompany.myapp;

import java.io.IOException;
import java.io.PrintWriter;

import com.aleax.blight.TemplateException;
import com.aleax.blight.TemplateManager;

import example.mycompany.myapp.templates.MyTemplate;

public class MyApp
{
    public static void main(final String[] args) throws TemplateException, IOException
    {
        // Create a new template
        MyTemplate template = new MyTemplate();
        
        // Configure the template to send its output to System.out
        PrintWriter out = new PrintWriter(System.out);
        template.setOutput(out);

        // Compile and execute the template
        TemplateManager.execute(template);

        // Ensure the output is written before the app terminates
        out.flush();
    }
}
</source>

<h4>MyTemplate.java</h4>

<p>The template extends AbstractTemplate and must implement the <code>execute()</code> method.
Any comments within this method are written to the template output when the method is called
on the compiled template. The example template also contains a single setter to pass in the 
customer details to include in the template output.</p>

<source>
package example.mycompany.myapp.templates;

import java.io.IOException;
import com.aleax.blight.AbstractTemplate;

public class MyTemplate extends AbstractTemplate
{
    @Override
    public void execute() throws IOException
    {
        /*Hello World!*/
    }
}
</source>

<h3>Libraries</h3>

<p>Download and unpack the bLight binary distribution into the lib directory.
The lib directory structure should end up with the following:</p>

<source>
lib/
`-- blight-dist/
    |-- LICENSE.txt
    `-- doc/
    `-- lib/
    |   |-- compiler-libs/
    |   |-- blight-compiler.jar
    |   `-- blight-core.jar
    `-- tools/
        |-- blight-ant-task.jar
        |-- blight-compiler-standalone.jar
        `-- blight-maven-plugin.jar
</source>

<h3>Build</h3>

<p>For basic use, bLight only requires a single library at runtime. 
The blight-core.jar will need to be added to the class path which you 
use to compile and run your project.</p>

<p>bLight templates must be compiled before they can be used. For a production
deployment, they should be pre-compiled using the bLight command-line tool.
The basic steps are:</p>

<ol>
	<li>Compile the entire application. This ensures that everything is at least syntactically valid.</li>
	<li>Run the bLight command-line compiler to pre-compile the templates.</li>
	<li>Java compile the pre-compiled templates.</li>
</ol>

<p>An example of how to do this is shown below.</p>

<source><![CDATA[
#!/bin/bash
javac -cp lib/blight-dist/lib/blight-core.jar -sourcepath src/main/java -d target/classes 
java -cp tools/blight-compiler-standalone.jar com.aleax.blight.compiler.BatchCompiler -s src/main/java -p example.mycompany.myapp.templates -o target/compiled-templates
javac -cp lib/blight-dist/lib/blight-core.jar:target/classes -sourcepath target/compiled-templates -d target/classes
]]></source>

<p>The application can then be run with the following:</p>

<source>
#!/bin/bash
java -cp lib/blight-dist/lib/blight-core.jar:target/classes example.mycompany.myapp.MyApp
</source>

<h3>Enabling dynamic template compilation</h3>

<p>Templates can be compiled at run-time for faster development without requiring an application 
restart after each change. To enable this functionality, the blight-compiler and template java
sources must be added to the classpath, and the templates must not be pre-compiled until the
application is packaged.</p>

<p>The compilation script just needs the template compilation steps commented-out:</p>

<source><![CDATA[
#!/bin/bash
javac -cp lib/blight-dist/lib/blight-core.jar -sourcepath src/main/java -d target/classes 
#java -cp lib/blight-compiler-1.0.0-jar-with-dependencies.jar com.aleax.blight.compiler.BatchCompiler -s src/main/java -p example.mycompany.myapp.templates -o target/compiled-templates
#javac -cp lib/blight-dist/lib/blight-core.jar:target/classes -sourcepath target/compiled-templates -d target/classes
]]></source>

<p>The application can then be run with the following:</p>

<source>
#!/bin/bash
java -cp lib/blight-dist/lib/blight-core.jar:tools/blight-compiler-standalone.jar:src/main/java:target/classes example.mycompany.myapp.MyApp
</source>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
  
